Guide to the Anthony R. Soto Papers, 1950-1993
Department of Special Collections
Soto, Anthony R. Papers,
1950-1993
M0763
Soto, Anthony R.
5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection includes manuscripts, subject files, and newsclippings, primarily relating to Soto's research and teaching on Hispanics in the Catholic Church and migrant workers in California.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1995.
Biography
Professor at the School of Social Work, San Jose State University.
Scope and Content Notes
Manuscripts, subject files, and newsclippings, primarily relating to Soto's research and teaching on Hispanics in the Catholic Church and migrant workers in California.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Catholic Church.; Mexican Americans.; Migrant labor.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. History of California Farmworkers in Newspaper clippings
  - Spiralbound copies of transcribed interview of Antonio Soto by Josie Negrete, UC Santa Cruz (first date given 7/2/93) (Box 1)
  - Essay, "Dimensions of Religiosity in the Mexican American Community of the New Almaden Quicksilver Mines, 1848-1908." By AS (Box 1)
    Includes attached letter to and comments from Dr. Matt Meier, History, Santa Clara Univ.
  - Transcribed interview of AS by Gloria Cuadraz, (Ph.D., UC Berkeley, 1993). (Box 1)
    Attached letter from Dr. Cuadraz.
  - "History of Our Lady of Guadalupe parish" by AS (Box 1)
  - Essay, "Chicano Workers in the New Almaden Quicksilver Minse of Northern California, 1848-1908. By AS in Chicano Social & Political History in the 19th Century, ed. Griswold del Castillo & Hidalgo (Floricanto Press, 1994) (3 copies) (Box 1)
  - Notes on "Life history method" by John Clausen (Box 1)
  - Assorted course papers/family histories from AS' students in Mexican American Graduate Studies 125, SJSU (Box 1)
  - "Agricultural Continuum: A Descriptive Study of the Farmworker Population and the Settling-Out Process" By Dept. Health, Education & Welfare. (Box 1)
  - "The Church in California and the Chicano: A Sociological Analysis," / Anthony Soto. -- In Grito Del Sol 4:1 (1979)., 5 Copies (Box 1)
  - Selections from Virgilio Elizondo's Christianity & Culture (p. 174-194). (Box 1)
  - "The Church" from Meier & Rivera's Dictionary of Mex Am History (entry written by AS). (Box 1)
    Also typescript copy.
  - "The New Almaden Quicksilver Mines" from Meier & Rivera's Dictionary of Mex Am History (entry written by AS). (Box 1)
    Typescript copy.
  - Multiple copies, AS article' "Ethnic Minorities within a Religious Institution:" from Migration Today 7:5 (1979). (Box 1)
    Also one complete issue.
  - "Futuro Sacerdote" flyer for church discussion group, 1970. (Box 1)
  - Regeneracion (journal)1:9 (1970) (Box 1)
  - "Migration Life Histories of Chicanos--as Told by themselves" / by Anthony Soto(July 1985) (Box 1)
  - "Principles of Intervention and the Religious Values of Minorities" / by Anthony Soto(3/26/82) (Box 1)
  - "The Socio-Historical Background of the Problem" / by Anthony Soto(3/26/82) (Box 1)
  - "Chicano Self-Help in Economic Development: Case Studies, Past and Present" / by Anthony Soto3/21/85), 3 copies (Box 1)
  - "Power Analysis Applied to Religious Institutions: A Case Study" / by Anthony Soto(3/18/81) (Box 1)
  - "Catholicism in China Today: Accomodation or Anachronism?" (sic) / by Anthony Soto(7/20/84) (Box 1)
  - "Community-Based Economic Development and Chicanos: A Case Study" / by Anthony Soto11/19/83, 2 copies (Box 1)
  - "Migrant Workers" (Box 1)
    Newsletters from Bishops Committee for Migrant Workers, March & April-May 1962 -- News release, Migratory Worker Program, 1/22/63 -- Ad, Calif State Dept of Employment for Migrant Labor with wages offered, 10/19/62 -- Correspondence: AS to Msgr. William Quinn, Dan Villanueva to AS -- Misc. notes on numbers of Spanish-speaking, employment stats. -- Misc. newspaper articles on migrant labor, April-May 1962
  - Notes on interview with Paul Sedillo, 7/16/76 (Box 1)
    Cassette tape of interview
  - Liturgy Chicano (Box 1)
    "Bautismo de Aztlan" notes and charts
  - PADRES (Padres Asociados para Derechos Religiosos Educativos y Sociales (Box 1)
    [Chicano priests org.] -- Misc. newsletters, docs, 1974-75 -- Correspondence
  - "1960-78 Materials--old text" (Box 1)
    Copy of article on formation of BCSS (Monitor, 2/10/77) -- Copy of "Official US Census Bureau Preliminary Spanish Language Population Stats," 1/24/72 -- Letter from Paul Sedillo (Div. for Spanish-Speaking) to Reynaldo (presumably Reynaldo Flores), 11/24/71. Documents priests' resistance to offices for Spanish-speaking -- Newsletter from PADRES documenting convention issues and 'walkout,' by Reynaldo Flores, 2/10/70. -- Dissertation notes -- Copy news article on Guadalupe Church, 9/23/73 -- Regeneracion, 1:8 (1970)
  - "Bracero Investigation" (Box 1)
    Memo to Charles O'Brien, Asst Attny Gen from Harry Cooper, Special Agent, docs on working conditions, 12/29/59 -- Newsletter of Imperial Valley Farmers Assn. -- Statement by AFL-CIO Executive Council on Migratory Agricultural Labor -- "Statement of Importation of Japanese Farmworkers," Cal State Federation of Labor, 4/23/57
  - "Migrant Family" (Box 1)
    Docs on lettuce boycott, Proposition 22, 1972
  - Misc. Farmworker/migrant labor docs (Box 1)
  - San Jose community/education docs (Box 1)
    Flyer for Colegio Jacinto Trevino -- list of lectures by AS, 1973-74 -- Barrio youth conference flyers -- "Making it Happen: About the Community Organization Steps" training pamphlet -- Newsletter, Division for Spanish-Speaking
  - Book: Farm Labor Fact book, U.S. Dept. of Labor (Box 1)
  - La Voz de la Tierra newspaper (vol 1: nos. 1-4) (Box 1)
  - El Malcriado newspaper (UFW), 5:10 (Sept 72) and 4:12 (1/71) and 12/29/72. & Basta: La Historia de Nuestra Lucha (Box 1)
  - Essay by Lydia Aguirre, "The meaning of the Chicano Movement", La Opinion del Campo newspaper 1:2 (March 76), Denver, Colorado. (Box 1)
    Also includes: National Catholic Reporter, Opinion magazine 2/14/75 -- Selections from World and Peoples' World
  - Misc. Chicano newspapers (Box 1)
    El Tecolote 2:4 (10/27/71) -- Sedition 1:5 (1/10/72) -- La Voz del Pueblo 2:9 (Nov 71) -- La Voz de la Raza 1:8 (6/1/70) -- Chicanismo 3:1A (Nov 71) -- Nuestra Tierra 2:1 (5/4/79) by MEChA at SJSU -- Salt of the Earth 1:10 (Dec 71)
  - Braceros & Migrant Workers: scrapbook, 1950s & 60s, 1 v.: brown cover; folio size (Box 1)
  - Misc. news clippings on migrant labor camps, Chicanos in San Jose, 1975-80 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Farm Workers in Imperial Valley and Southern California: scrapbook, 1961, 1 v.: brown cover; folio size (Volume 2)
- Series 2. Papers for Stanford Chicano Library Archives
  - San Luis Rey Mission & Seminary 1950-61 (Box 2)
    Letter, Francis Guest, O.F.M. to AS, 3/15/91 -- B & W photo, Anthony Soto & George Mroczkowski, 1958. -- Letter, Huntington Library to AS, 1991. -- Pamphlet: "Indian Life at Mission San Luis Rey" -- Pamphlet: "San Luis Rey Mission Fiesta" 1959 w/pic of AS & G. Mroczkowski. -- Copy, "Mission San Luis Rey, California--Excavations in the Sunken Gardens" by AS, KIVA: Journal of Arizona Archaeological and Historical Society 26:4 (1961). -- Article: "Uncovering the Past at Mission San Luis Rey," featuring AS, written by Frank Graham, Westways (May 1958). -- Misc. news articles on San Luis Rey
  - Booklet: "Cultural Historic Landscape Preservation Proposal," Mission San Luis Rey, 10/25/90. (Box 2)
  - Confederacion de la Raza Unida (CRU) (Box 2)
    President's Report, CRU 3/19/72 -- CRU Constitution, 3/16/72 -- Letters, Jack Ybarra, CRU President to Father AS at Guadalupe Church, 1971-2. -- Press release on Fiesta de las Rosas boycott, 5/16/69 -- Misc. meeting minutes, 1969-70s -- List of CRU affiliates
  - Book/let: "The Chicano and the Church: Study of a Minority Within a Religious Institution," Marfel Associates, March 1975. (Box 2)
  - Essays by AS (Box 2)
    "The Structure of Society According to Duns Scotus," by AS, Franciscan Studies 12:1 (March 1952). -- "Los Chicanos y las Iglesias," estudios ecumenicos, 11/71. -- "Painful Migration: The Life History of a Mexican Immigrant," June 1973. -- "Bracero Mission," Apostolic Perspectives 3:2 (Summer 1958). -- "Sociology of the Migrant Family," Franciscan Educational Conference Proceedings, vol. 41 (Aug 1960). -- "Una Platica: Mexican American Approaches to Death and Dying," by AS and Jose Villa. -- "Practical Aspects of Caring for the Dying in a Mexican American Culture," panel presentation at Stanford University, "Dilemmas in the Care of the Dying," October 1983. -- "The Spirit of the Cursillo" in Ultreya 4:6 (June 1962). -- "Early Beginnings of the Cursillo Movement in the Bay Area, California" mss. -- "The Cursillo Movement" mss. -- Catholic Rural Life, complete copies of June 1960 and July 1960, featuring articles by AS ("Human Misery for Sale" parts 1 and 2). -- Pamphlet: "Migrants in Your Parish" -- Homiletic & Pastoral Review, 6/61, 9/61, 3/69 featuring -- "Migrants in Your Parish," 6/61 -- Letters to editor about "Migrants" article, 9/61 -- "Getting Through to Our Spanish Speaking," 3/69 -- "The Cursillo Movement," in The Inner Crusade, by Tom Hennessey (Loyola U Press, 1965) -- "The Bracero Story," Commonweal 71:9 (11/27/59)
  - "Migration Life Histories" (Box 2)
    "Migration Life Histories of Chicanos--as told by themselves" July 1985 -- Various drafts of life histories, 3 color slides, one color photo of Sara Segovia
  - New Almaden Quicksilver Mines (Box 2)
    Galleys of AS' article on Quicksilver Mines for Floricanot Press -- Corr: Stanford Libraries to AS -- AS to Floricanto Press (multiple) -- AS to Griswold del Castillo.(multiple) -- b & w photos, apparently from Stanford archives
  - New Almaden--Loose materials & photos (Box 2)
    Misc. news clippings on mines, mine area, local folks -- Misc. notes, documents, interview notes
  - "Chicano Reaction to Social Change in N. California, 1848-1908" (Box 2)
    Mss. returned with letter (11/18/77) from Doyce Nunis, Southern California Quarterly.
  - Book/let: bound copy of "Chicano Reaction to Social Change in N. California, 1848-1908" (Box 2)
  - Sonoran Migration (Box 2)
    Notes from research at Arizona Historical Society, Tucson, AZ -- Misc. notes
  - Book/let: "Spanish Speaking Protestant Churches of the Mayfair Area" by Loretta Shea and Nancy Delaney (student paper?) (Box 2)
  - Book: New Almaden & the Mexican, M.A. thesis by Francisco Valencia (Committee chair, AS) (Box 2)
  - Book/let: "Santa Teresa Laboratory: A Place in History (IBM facility built on/near site of Almaden mines?) (Box 2)
  - Book: Cinnabar Hills: The Quicksilver Days of New Almaden, Milton Lanyon & Laurence Bulmore. (Box 2)
  - Misc. news clippings from San Jose Mercury (Box 2)
  - Misc. Chicano newspapers (Box 2)
    Chicanismo (Stanford), June 1970, November 1971, January 1971 -- El Sol (Salinas), 9/22/71, 11/10/71 & 11/24/71 -- El Tiempo, April 1972 -- La Gente de Aztlan, January 1974 & March 1974 -- entrelineas 1:3, April 1971 -- Venceremos (Las Gorras Negras, Albuquerque) 1:2 June 1971 -- La Malcriada 1:1, 6/8/73. -- Spartan Daily (SJSU), 4/27/72 -- Migration Today 2:3, May 1974. -- PADRES 2:12, July 1973 -- La Raza 1:12 (Sept 73) & 1:11 -- The Forumeer 17, Nov 1971 -- Que Tal (typescript) -- Misc. news clippings
  - Index notecards (Box 2)
  - Three cassette tapes: Bulmore, Mrs. Perham, and AHS (Kerman?, 12/76) (Box 2)
- Series 3. Research of relationship of Chicano people to the Catholic Church
  - "Parishes of Guadalupe" (Box 3)
    Copies of correspondence of Commission on Social Justice w/Archbishop McGucken over use of Cathedral for 'political' meetings, March 1973. -- Questionaire on issues of discrimination, Guadalupe Church, 1975. -- Church pamphlets
  - Catholic Council for Spanish Speaking (Box 3)
    Minutes, Bishops' Committee for Spanish Speaking, West Coast Board Seminar, 4/25/68 -- [Includes references to James L. Vizzard, Herman Gallegos]
  - Catholic Social Service--"Report of the Committee on the Problems of Mexican-Americans in California" by Bishops Committee for the Spanish-Speaking, West Coast Regional Office. (Box 3)
  - Catolicos por la Raza (Box 3)
    Misc. notes and news clippings about protest by CPLR at St. Basil's Cathedral, 12/24/69 -- La Raza newspaper, 2:10 (12/69) and 2:9 (11/69).
  - Encuentro Nacional II, August 1977 (Box 3)
    "Another View of the II Encuentro Nacional Hispano" by Casimira Rodriguez, 10/29/77 -- Misc. news clippings about Encuentro -- Statement from Pope about Encuentro (English & Spanish), 8/12/77 -- Statement, "Unidad en Pluralismo" by Segundo Encuentro Hispano Nacional, Washington DC, 8/18/77
  - Cursillo--lists of cursillo participants, #1 (2/9/61) (Box 3)
    Correspondence, Sub-Secretariate of Spanish Cursillos, 3/18/68 -- Correspondence, Cursillos in Christianity, Archdiocese of S.F., 5/15/70 -- Misc. news clippings
  - Chicano Deacon Program (Box 3)
    Notes on Asilomar weekend, 10/28/77 -- Correspondence from Anthony McGuire evaluating Chicano Deacon program, 2/24/77 -- Essay: "Why I Want To Become a Deacon" by Phillip V. Marquez, 11/18/74 (long mss of work published in Monitor) -- Essay by Felipe (Phillip?) Marquez, talk at St. Patrick's Seminary, Mountain View, 2/20/75 -- Report on Chicano Deacon training program, budget (no date) -- Working Paper: "Spanish Speaking Diaconate Program," Div. for Spanish Speaking, Midwestern Office, 8/1970 -- Program, Diaconate ordination, Our Lady of Guadalupe, 12/12/74 -- Misc. clippings
  - Bishops Meeting, Region XI, 2/1/77 (Box 3)
    "Report on Minority Affairs" by Juan Arzube, Auxiliary Bishop of Los Angeles, to Region XI bishops meeting, 5/2/73 -- Report by Robert Gonzales, Division for Spanish-Speaking, US Catholic Conference -- Census figures on Catholics, Hispanics, 1970 -- Lecture notes, by Robert Gonzales. -- Correspondence to Reynaldo Flores from Bp. Leo Maher, 12/22/71 (ongoing dispute over numbers of Mexican-American Catholics) -- Lecture notes, Bishop Roger Mahony, "The Role of the Church, Faith, and Collegial Relationships."
  - Centro Pastoral--multiple pamphlets from Centro Pastoral, San Jose, California (Box 3)
    Notes on Comunidades de Base (CEBs)
  - Chicano Priests Organization (Box 3)
    Essay by Renaldo Flores, OFM, "La Raza, The Church, and Leadership" -- Misc. meeting minutes, Chicano Priests Organization (CPO), 1971-73 -- Report on fostering dialogue/communication among Catholic Spanish-speaking in Santa Clara County, no date -- La Voz del Pueblo newspaper, 2:10 (12/1971) -- Copy of correspondence from Philip Mirenda, Carl Swenson Contracting Company to Archbishop McGucken, 12/5/69, complaining about Father McEntee/Poggi's involvement in protest, 12/3/69. -- Misc. news clippings, S.F. protest, 5/5/71
  - Chicano Church-General (Box 3)
    Misc. news clippings -- "the chicano and the church" by Alberto Carrillo, CSSR. -- Draft essay, "The Sociological Failure of the Catholic Church towards the Chicano," by AS
  - Encuentro Nacional, June 1972 (Box 3)
    (report)
  - Chicano Bishops--Misc. news clippings (Box 3)
  - Chapter IV--Materials 1940-60 (Box 3)
    [apparently, Ch. IV of Soto dissertation] -- "Excerpts from Report of Field Trip into Northern States," BCSS, February 1957 -- Notes from McDonnell & Ronald Burke interviews -- Notebook, Journal beginning 6/19/56, apparently tracking AS's route serving bracero/migrant communities throughout Northern California.
  - Kellogg Mission Band (Box 3)
    Pages 62-142 of thesis/dissertation? on Spanish Mission Band. -- Correspondence, from Diocese of San Diego to Edward Browning, St. Patrick's seminary, Menlo Park
  - Mexican-Americans 1940-60, "The Spanish-Speaking of the Southwest and West," Social Action Dept, Natl. Catholic Welfare Conference. (Box 3)
  - Archdiocese, S.F. (Box 3)
    "Explantion of Archdiocesan Financial Report...," 2/10/72 -- Correspondence, Archdiocese of S.F. to AS, notifying of pastoral replacement at OLG, 7/6/72.
  - BCSS, 1960 - (Box 3)
    Correspondence -- Multiple survey reports, "1965 Report, Pastoral Care of Spanish-Speaking" -- Multiple newsletters
  - "A brief history of the BCSS, 1967-68..and the Division for Spanish Speaking, US Catholic Conference, 1969-72. Dated March 1973. (Box 3)
  - Oral History--Lucio Bernabe notes (Box 3)
  - Mex 1848 (Box 3)
    "Planning, Politics and Plunder: The Missions and Indian Pueblos of Hispanic California" by Daniel Garr -- "Power and Priorities: Church-State Boundary Disputes in Spanish California" by Daniel Garr -- Misc. news clippings
  - Mining--Glenna Matthews (Box 3)
    Copy of Matthews article, "The Community Study: Ethnicity & Success in San Jose," Journal of Interdisciplinary History 7:2 (Autumn 1976).
  - Materials1848-1910 (Box 3)
    Misc. notecards, sources,
  - Alemany ab.--misc. notes (Box 3)
  - Quinn (Box 3)
    Correspondence, Archbishop John Quinn to Ricardo Garcia, 12/5/77. General praise, demurs at 'separate seminary program for Spanish-speaking.' -- Monitor newspaper, 4/28/77, headline: Quinn's installation
  - Chap. III--Orig. materials, 1910-40 (Box 3)
    Clippings, SJ Mercury, 3/30/78 "San Jose's Barrio" -- Misc. notes, notecards
  - Mexicans in California: Gov. Young's Commission Report, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Stevens-Arroyo, Tony (Box 3)
    Correspondence
  - Broadbent, Eliz. Excerpts from Distribution of Mexican Population in United States (S.F.R.C., 1972, orig. U of Chicago, 1941). (Box 3)
  - Church--San Diego (Box 3)
    Correspondence, Paul Sedillo, BCSS to Manuel Guillen, MexAm Commission, San Bernardino -- Essays by Juan Hurtado: "Stress Among Priests," course paper, 11/15/74; "Role of Cath Church in Chicano Community," course paper, 5/15/75; "Brief Report on Coachella and Imperial Valley"; News clippings on Father Juan Hurtado
  - Church--Arizona (misc. news clippings) (Box 3)
  - Church--Los Angeles (Box 3)
    Copy Correspondence, Roger Luna, L.A.--Reynaldo Flores -- News clipping on L.A./Orange diocese
  - Church--New Mexico (Box 3)
    Misc. news clippings by Moises Sandoval
  - Church--Other places (Box 3)
    "Cursillo: Hispanic Catholics divided by Monterey Diocese issues" Californian -- Copies of correspondence between Roberto Gonzales, Div. for Span-Spkg and Sylvester Treinen, Bishop of Idaho.
  - San Bernardino Diocese (Box 3)
    Clippings from National Catholic Reporter, 11/17/78, 10/27/78, 9/29/78, -- Corresondence from Fr. Juan Hurtado to Apostolic Delegate Jean Jadot, 5/15/78 -- Misc. clippings
  - Church-Stockton (Box 3)
    "Third Monthly Progress Report of the Catholic Council for the Spanish Speaking of the Diocese of Stockton, 6/14/68. -- "Fourth Monthly Progress Report of the Catholic Council for the Spanish Speaking of the Diocese of Stockton, 7/26/68.
  - Church--Texas (clippings on dispute in Beeville, TX) (Box 3)
  - Protestant Churches (Box 3)
    List of Prot. churches with Spanish language services in San Jose area).
  - hotos--Chicano & Church (Box 3)
    Liz & Ramiro Gutierrez, San Jose -- Unknown Chicano/Mexicano -- Unknown child -- Comunidad
  - Priests--Married--New Ministries (Box 3)
    "Statement of Support for CORPUS" (Corps of Reserve Priests United for Service) by Alberto Carrillo -- National Catholic Reporter article about AS as former priest -- Essay by Joan Ohanneson, no title, about priests who leave ministry, featuring AS and San Jose Opportunities Industrialization Center (OIC). Handwritten note, June 1974.
  - Fiesta de las Rosas (Box 3)
    Misc. clippings and documents around boycott organized by Confederacion de la Raza Unida, 6/1/69 -- San Jose Maverick 1:5, July 1969
  - Latin American Conference (Box 3)
  - Mosqueda, Chicanos & Church (Box 3)
    Unpub. mss. "Chicanos, Catholicism, and Political Ideology," 2/26/77 -- Unpub. mss. "An Evaluation of the impact of Catholicism on Political Ideology of Chicano Community," 5/2/79
  - USCC National (Box 3)
  - PADRES (Misc. docs, meeting notes) (Box 3)
  - USCC West (Box 3)
    "Report of major activities 1968-69, Western Region, Div. for Spanish-Speaking, US Catholic Conference." -- Correspondence log, incoming, March 1-April 20, 1971 -- Correspondence log, outgoing, March 1-April 20, 1971 -- Misc. notes, documents
  - Sacraments--MexAmer Issues Conference (Box 3)
    List of resolutions passed at Mexican-American, Spanish Surname Issues Conference, 3/10/68.
  - Santa Clara University (Box 3)
    Misc. clippings around 11/21/72 protest by Chicano students -- SJ Merc clipping, 11/21/72, p. A1
  - Women in the Church (Box 3)
    Misc. documents on HERMANAS (org of Chicana religious and lay women) -- Notes, Hermanas State Conference, 11/19/77
  - PADRES newsletter (Box 3)
    Mailing list of PADRES members -- Misc. PADRES newsletters 2:8 (Feb 73), (March 73), (Sept 73), 4:3 (May 74), 4:4 (July 74), 4:5 (Nov 74), 4:6 (April 75), 5:2 (Oct 75), 6:1 (Jan 76), 6:2 (Summer 76), 6:3 (Fall 76), 6:4 (Winter 77), 7:2 (Spring 77), 7:3 (Summer 77)
  - West Coast Coalition (Box 3)
    Misc. documents -- Multiple membership rosters -- Short typescript history, "Information for Mrs. Blanche Oran..."
  - Misc. Publications (Box 3)
    Booklet: San Jose's St. Joseph's: History and Guide of St. Joseph's Church (with notes by AS) -- San Jose Mercury Commemmorative Issue, 1851-1976 -- La Voz del Pueblo 3:7 (Sept. 72)